So what is this data analysis process?
إذًا فما هي عملية تحليل البيانات هذه؟
We broke it up into five steps: question,
قسمناها إلى خمس خطوات: السؤال،
wrangle, explore, draw conclusions and communicate.
المعالجة، الاستكشاف، رسم الاستنتاجات والتواصل.
This process will help you understand,
ستساعدك هذه العملية على فهم،
explore and use your data
استكشاف واستخدام بياناتك
intelligently so that you make the most of the information you're given.
بذكاء مما يجعلك تُنشئ معظم المعلومات المُعطاة لك.
Whether you're building your reporting dashboard,
فإذا كنت تبني لوحة المعلومات التقريرية،
analyzing A-B test results or doing more advanced analysis with machine learning and AI.
تحليل نتائج اختبار A-B أو تقوم بإجراء تحليل أكثر تقدمًا باستخدام التعليم الآلي و AI.
Let's see what each step is about.
لنرى عما تدور كل خطوة.
The data analysis process always starts with asking questions.
تبدأ عملية تحليل البيانات دائمًا بطرح الأسئلة.
Sometimes, you're already given a data set and
في بعض الأحيان، تُعطى مجموعة من البيانات
glance over it to figure out good questions to ask.
لتلقي نظرة عليها فتخرج بأسئلة جيدة لتطرحها.
Other times, your questions come first,
وفي أحيان أخري، تأتي أسئلتك أولًا
which will determine what kinds of data you'll gather later.
مما يحدد أي أنواع البيانات ستجمع لاحقًا.
In both cases, you should be thinking: what am I trying to find out?
وفي كلتا الحالتين، ينبغي عليك أن تفكر: ما الذي أحاول اكتشافه؟
Is there a problem I'm trying to solve?
هل توجد مشكلة أحاول حلها؟
For example, what are the characteristics of students who pass their projects?
على سبيل المثال، ما هي خصائص التلاميذ الذين سينجحون في مشاريعهم؟
How can I better stock my store with products people want to buy?
كيف أضيف مخزونًا أفضل لمتجري ببضائع يود الناس شراؤها؟
In the real world, you often deal with multiple sets of massive amounts of data,
في العالم الحقيقي، تتعامل بشكل دائم بمجموعات عدة لكميات كبيرة من البيانات،
all in different forms.
جميعها في أشكال مختلفة.
The right questions can really help you focus on relevant parts of
بإمكان الأسئلة الصحيحة مساعدتك على التركيز على الأجزاء المتعلقة
your data and direct your analysis towards meaningful insights.
ببياناتك وتُحول تحليلك نحو الرؤى ذات المغزى.
In this course, we're going to focus on use cases with one set of
في هذه الدورة التدريبية، سنقوم بالتركيز على استخدام الحالات بمجموعة واحدة
data and practice posing
من البيانات وسنتدرب على طرح
relevant and interesting questions that lead to valuable results.
الأسئلة المتعلقة والشيقة والتي ستؤدي بنا إلى نتائج قيّمة.
Once you have your questions,
بمجرد حصولك على أسئلتك،
you'll need to wrangle your data to help you answer them.
ستحتاج إلى معالجة بياناتك لتساعدك على الإجابة عليها.
By that, I mean making sure you have all the data you need in great quality.
وأقصد بذلك أنه عليك التأكد من حصولك على جميع البيانات التي تحتاجها بجودة عالية جدًا.
There are three parts to this step.
توجد ثلاث أجزاء لهذه الخطوة.
First, you gather your data.
أولًا، اجمع بياناتك.
If you are already given that data,
إذا كانت البيانات مُعطاة لك من البداية،
then all you need to do is open it,
فكل ما عليك فعله هو فتحها،
like importing it into a Jupyter Notebook.
استيرادها في Jupyter Notebook.
If you weren't provided data,
أما إذا لم تُمنح البيانات،
you need think carefully about what data would be most helpful in
سيكون عليك التفكير بحرص عن أي البيانات ستُفيدك أكثر
answering your questions and then collect them from all the sources available.
في إجابة أسئلتك ومن ثم اجمعهم من جميع المصادر المتاحة.
Second, you assess your data to identify
ثانيًا، قيّم بياناتك لتحديد
any problems in your data's quality or structure.
أي مشكلات في جودة أو بنية البيانات.
Third, you clean your data.
ثالثًا، نظف بياناتك.
This often involves modifying, replacing,
يشمل هذا دائمًا تعديل، استبدال
or moving data to ensure that your data set
أو نقل البيانات للتأكد من أن مجموعة بياناتك
is as high quality and well-structured as possible.
ذات جودة عالية وبنية سليمة قدر الإمكان.
This wrangling step is all about getting
تدور فكرة خطوة المعالجة حول
the data you need in a form that you can work with.
الحصول على البيانات التي تحتاجها في شكل يُتيح لك العمل بها.
Sometimes, this step will be really easy and straightforward.
في بعض الأحيان، تكون هذه الخطوة مباشرة وفي غاية السهولة.
Other times, it's a little more tricky.
وفي أحيان أخرى، تكون خادعة قليلًا.
Now that you've wrangle your data,
والآن وبعد أن عالجت بياناتك،
you'll hopefully have good quality, clean data.
لحسن الحظ سيصبح لديك بيانات نظيفة وذات جودة عالية.
Which means, you're ready to explore.
مما يعني أنك مستعد للاستكشاف.
EDA or exploratory data analysis is about exploring and then augmenting
إن EDA أو تحليل البيانات الاستكشافي يدور حول استكشاف وتعزيز
your data to maximize the potential of your analyses, visualizations, and models.
بياناتك لتكبير إمكانيات تحليلاتك، تصوراتك ونماذجك.
Exploring involves finding patterns in your data,
يشتمل الاستكشاف على إيجاد أنماط في بياناتك،
visualizing relationships in your data
تصور العلاقات في بياناتك
and just building intuition about what you're working with.
وبناء حدس عما تعمل به.
After exploring, you can do things like remove outliers
بعد الاستكشاف، يُمكنك القيام بأشياء مثل إزالة العناصر الخارجية
and create new and more descriptive features from existing data,
وإنشاء خصائص جديدة وأكثر وصفًا من البيانات الحالية،
also known as feature engineering.
وهي تُعرف أيضًا بهندسة الخصائص.
Many times modifying and engineer your data properly and
يؤدي تعديل وهندسة بياناتك بشكل صحيح ومبدع ، في أغلب الأحيان إلى
even creatively can significantly increase the quality of your analysis.
زيادة ملحوظة في جودة تحليلك.
As you become more familiar with your data in this EDA step,
وكلما تعرفت أكثر على بياناتك في خطوة EDA،
you'll often revisit previous steps.
كلما زُرت الخطوات السابقة باستمرار.
For example, you might discover new problems in your data and go back to wrangle them.
على سبيل المثال، من المحتمل أن تكتشف مشاكل جديدة في بياناتك وتعود لمعالجتها.
Or you might discover exciting,
أو يُحتمل اكتشاف أنماط شيقة
unexpected patterns and decide to refine your questions.
وغير متوقعة فتقرر على إثرها العودة لصقل أسئلتك.
The data analysis process isn't always linear.
إن عملية تحليل البيانات لا تسير في خط مستقيم دائمًا.
This exploratory step in particular is very intertwined with the rest of the process.
إن خطوة الاستكشاف هذه، خصيصًا، متشابكة مع بقية العملية.
It's usually where you discover and learn the most about your data.
فهي حيث تكتشف وتتعلم أكثر الأمور عن بياناتك.
After you've done your exploratory data analysis,
بعد انتهائك من تحليل البيانات الاستكشافي،
you want to draw conclusions or even make predictions.
سترغب في رسم استنتاجات أو حتى وضع التنبؤات.
For example, predicting which students will
على سبيل المثال، التنبؤ برسوب التلاميذ
fail a project so you can reach out to those students.
في المشروع وبالتالي تستطيع الوصول لهؤلاء التلاميذ.
Or predicting which products are most likely
أو تنبؤ عن أي المنتجات ستكون أكثر
to sell so you can start your store appropriately.
مبيعًا فتبدأ بتخزينها بشكل مناسب.
From a data science perspective,
ومن منظور علم البيانات،
this step is typically approached with machine learning or
نصل إلى هذه الخطوة نموذجيًا باستخدام التعليم الآلي
inferential statistics that are beyond the scope of this course.
أو الإحصاء الاستنتاجية التي تتخطى نطاق هذه الدورة التدريبية.
But there are additional courses on Udacity
ولكن توجد دورات تدريبية إضافية على Udacity
they can take on these topics, if you're interested.
حيث يقومون بشرح هذه الموضوعات، إذا كانت لديك الرغبة في ذلك.
Those are linked in instructor resources below.
وتوجد روابط هذه الدورات التدريبية في مصادر الموجِه أسفله.
This course will help you form a solid foundation on drawing
ستساعدك هذه الدورة التدريبية على تكوين أساس صلب عن رسم
conclusions from summarizing data with descriptive statistics.
الاستنتاجات من تلخيص البيانات مع الإحصائيات الوصفية.
Finally, you need to communicate your results to others.
وأخيرًا، تحتاج إلى توصيل نتائجك إلى الآخرين.
This is one of the most important skills you can develop.
وتُعد هذه الخطوة أهم مهارة يمكنك تعلمها.
Your analysis is only as valuable as your ability to communicate it.
تقاس قيمة تحليلك بقدرتك على توصليه.
You often need to justify and convey meaning in the insights you found.
تحتاج دائمًا إلى تبرير وتمرير المعنى في الرؤى التي تجدها.
Or if your end goal is to build a system,
أو إذا كان هدفك النهائي هو بناء نظام،
like a movie recommender or a news feed ranking algorithm,
مثل موصي أفلام أو خوارزمية تحديد مرتبة مقالات الأخبار،
you usually to share what you've built,
فأنت غالبًا تشارك ما بنيته،
explain how you reach design decisions and report how well it performs.
تشرح كيفية الوصول إلى قرارات التصميم وتقرر كيفية أداؤها بكفاءة.
You can communicate results in many ways.
يمكنك توصيل النتائج بطرق عديدة.
Reports, slide decks, blog posts,
التقارير، المنصات المنزلقة، المدونات،
emails, presentations, or even conversations.
البريد الالكتروني، عرض البيانات أو حتى بالمحادثات.
Regardless of your method of communication,
بغض النظر عن طريقة التواصل،
data visualization will always be very valuable.
سيظل تصور البيانات ذو قيمة كبيرة.
So those are the five steps of the data analysis process: question,
إذًا كانت تلك الخطوات الخمس لعملية تحليل البيانات: الأسئلة،
wrangle, explore, draw conclusions and communicate.
المعالجة، الاستكشاف، رسم الاستنتاجات والتواصل.
Before jumping into how you go through this process on a real data set in Python,
قبل الانتقال إلى كيفية المضي في هذه العملية عن طريق مجموعة بيانات حقيقية في Python
we are going to work on building intuition for each step.
سنعمل على بناء حدس عن كل خطوة.